NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services Files. 6174/003
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services Files
1960-1998
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers
6174/003
73 cubic feet
3 linear feet
Correspondence, reports, publications.
This collection consists of NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services' reports, subject and correspondence files.
7163966
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Patricia Leary
Date completed:
March 2011
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, May 2011
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA-NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Biographical / Historical
The Division of Research and Educational Services was created in 1974-75 from the merger of three departments, the Research Department, the Professional Services Department, and the Instructional Improvement Department.
The Department of Instructional Improvement was funded in part by a federal grant; when the grant money was discontinued in 1973, it was merged with the Research Department. The Professional Services Department was a small group that worked on policies related to certification and teacher issues and also coordinated statewide teacher conferences mandated by education law, and merged with the Research Department during the same time period. The head of the Research Department, Charles Santelli, became the director of the merged Research and Instructional Improvement Department. The name was changed shortly thereafter, in 1974-75, to the Division of Research and Educational Services.
The division was placed under the purview of the Second Vice President, Antonia Cortese (in 1985, Cortese was elected First Vice President). Charles Santelli remained the director of the division until his retirement in September of 2010. Dan Kinley took over for Santelli and remains head of the department as of 2011.
The department works closely with NYSUT's Field Services, Program Services, and Legislation departments and provides support to NYSUT's committees and task forces. It provides information on salary and contracts, statistics, New York state learning standards, assessments, graduation requirements and accountability systems, special education, professional development, financial support of public education, and higher education. The department regularly designs and analyzes phone and internet surveys of members and the general public. It also prepares Information Bulletins and Briefing Bulletins on emerging educational issues at the state and federal level.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services' reports, subject and correspondence files. Most of the material is from period 1960-1998. There are a few earlier reports from the 1950s and some as early as 1937.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6174/018: NYSUT's Division of Research and Educational Services, Maria Neira Files.
Arrangement
AFT (Conventions, Executive Council, QUEST, etc) AFT Educational Research and Dissemination Program: see Educational Research and Dissemination (ER&D) Program Accountability (see also Evaluation) Board of Regents: see Regents CETA/Job Training Partnership Act CUNY/ Community Colleges Certification (see also Task Force on the Teaching Profession; see also Teacher Education, Certification and Practice Board (TECAP)) Children at Risk (see also Dropouts) Competency-Based Teacher Education Conferences Disabilities (see also Handicapped/ Handicapping; see also Special Education) Dropouts (see also Children at Risk) Early Childhood Education Learning Trust (see also Effective Schools/ Effective Teaching Program) Education Reform (see also Effective Schools/ Effective Teaching Program) Educational Accountability: see Accountability Educational Conference Board (ECB) Educational Policy: see Task Force on Educational Policy Educational Research and Dissemination (ER&D) Program Effective Schools/ Effective Teaching Program Equal Educational Opportunity/EEO (see also Human Relations) Equity and Excellence in Educaton (see also Financing) Evaluation (see also Accountability) Financing: see State Aid/School Financing (see also Levittown v. Nyquist; see also Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education) Handicapped/ Handicapping (see also Disabilities; see also Special Education) Higher Education Human Relations/ Humanism in Education/ Human Rights (see also Equal Educational Opportunity/EEO) Levittown v. Nyquist (see also State Aid/School Financing; see also Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education) New York State/NYS Educational Conference Board: see Educational Conference Board New York State/NYS Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education: see Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education Pay Equity (see also Salaries) Professional Decision Making: see Restructuring > Regents Research and Educational Services Restructuring/Shared Decision Making Rubin Commission (see also State Aid/School Financing; see also Levittown v. Nyquist; see also Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education) Rural Schools: see Rubin Commission Salaries (see also Pay Equity) School Effectiveness: see Effective Schools/Effective Teaching Program School Financing: see State Aid/School Financing School Improvement: see Effective Schools/Effective Teaching Program School Reform: see Effective Schools (see also Education Reform) School Restructuring: see Restructuring/Shared Decision Making Shared Decision Making: see Restructuring/Shared Decision Making Special Education (see also Disabilities; see also Handicapped) Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education (see also State Aid/School Financing; see also Levittown v. Nyquist) State Aid/School Financing (see also Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education; see also Levittown v. Nyquist) Task Force on the Teaching Profession/ Task Force on Teaching as a Profession (see also Teacher Certification; see also Certification) Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education: see Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education (see also Financing) Teacher Certification: see Certification (see also Task Force on the Teaching Profession; see also Teacher Education, Certification and Practice Board (TECAP)) Teacher Education Conference Board (TECB) Teacher Education, Certification and Practice Board (TECAP) (see also Certification) Teacher Evaluation: see Evaluation Teacher Salary: see Salaries Tuition Tax Credits Youth at Risk: see Children at Risk
Teachers' union -- New York (State); New York State United Teachers; New York State United Teachers
7163966
- AACTE (American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education), 1967-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Report, "Progress and Prospects: The State of the Association," 1970; "Standards and Evaluative Criteria for the Accreditation of Teacher Education," December 1967; list of officers and committees, 1972; program for leadership institute, 1974; description of association, c. 1972; publication lists; correspondence
- AACTE (American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education) Conference, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  November 9-10, 1981. Conference program, "A Design for a School of Pedagogy"; book of the same name, published by U.S. Department of Education, 1980; draft document by U.S. Department of Education, "Questions and Answers Concerning the Education Consolidation and Improvement Act of 1981," chapters 1 and 2, October 1981; proposed implementation timeline for chapter 2; list of members of AACTE Executive Board; handwritten notes
- AAUP (American Association of University Professors), 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Report (mostly sardonic commentary) on the 59th annual meeting of AAUP, April 27-28, 1973, as observed by an NEA organizer, with cover letter from National Education Association director of Higher Education Program; summary of new AAUP contract provisions for salary determination, May 15, 1973; tally of active members by college campus, SUNY and CUNY, May 4, 1977
- ACCF (Associated Community College Faculties, NYSTA), 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Salary study compiled by SUNY central administration, 1970; comptroller's opinion re professional staff salaries as public information, January 13, 1972; other statistical data
- AFT Convention Exec. Committee, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  February 14-17, 1994. Printed convention resolutions; program
- AFT Convention, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Proposed constitutional amendments
- AFT Convention – Anaheim, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  December 16, 1992. Convention questionnaire
- AFT Convention, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  August 11-16, 1992. Report of Futures Committee; press releases; related materials
- AFT Convention, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  July 2-5, 1990. Special order of business: Children in Crisis in Urban Schools; press releases
- AFT Convention, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Printed convention resolutions; booklet, "Teachers under Dictatorship," a project of the AFT; conference report by United University Professions Task Force on Teacher education, "Colleagues in Reform"; related materials
- AFT Educational Research and Dissemination Program See: Educational Research and Dissemination Program
- AFT Executive Council, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  August 10, 1992. Talking points and background on the report of the AFT Futures Committee; proposed resolutions; agenda
- AFT Executive Council, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  November 16-20, 1992. Draft list of AFT priorities for national legislation and union goals; convention questionnaire; handwritten notes
- AFT Executive Council, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  List of AFT Executive Council committees and members 1992-94; budget proposal and financial statement, April 30, 1992; resolution for joint organizing coalition, State of Kentucky State Employee Organizing Campaign; draft policy paper, U.S. Education: The Task before Us; draft for discussion on incentives and accountability; other discussion papers; questionnaire re role of Executive Council in union; highlights of AFT national focus groups, by Peter D. Hart Research Associates, winter 1991; printed report by DGB (German trade union federation) and AFL-CIO, "German-American Trade Union Solidarity in the Struggle against Fascism: 1933-1945: How the American trade unions helped their persecuted German colleagues," April 1985
- AFT Executive Council Meeting, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  June 2-3, 1992. California constitutional amendment, The Parental Choice in Education Initiative, November 19, 1991; resolution re universal pension coverage; resolution, "Toward World-Class Standards: Preparing Tomorrow's Workforce"; fact sheets re health care expenditures, reform proposals
- AFT Executive Council, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  February 11-12, 1992. Chart of AFT funding proposals; memo proposing a national program to address the needs of children in crisis, January 30, 1992; handwritten notes
- AFT Executive Council, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  October 22-23, 1991. Memo re special meeting of the Education and Research Committee of the Executive Council, October 22, 1991; Executive Council survey results in graph format; sample of one filled-out survey, October 1991; draft discussion paper, Preliminary Recommendations of the AFT Futures Committee, September 24, 1991, with cover memo
- AFT Education for Democracy, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  November 19, 1992. Report and proposal, "Democracy's Untold Story: What World History Textbooks Neglect," by Paul A. Gagnon, sponsored by the Education for Democracy Project, published by American Federation of Teachers; press releases, newspaper clippings, and related materials
- AFT Quest Conference, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  May 1-3, 1981. Conference program brochure; sample of contract language on school discipline; sample discipline codes from state departments of education; resource paper on student crime, "Rights and Regulations: Who's Keeping Discipline in the Schools?" May 3, 1981; article reprint from the Public Interest, "Crime in American Public Schools," winter 1980
- AFT Quest Conference, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  April 8-10, 1983. Conference program brochure; resource papers on a variety of issues; Report of the 65th Annual Convention of the American Federation of Teachers, July 6-9, 1981; AFT issues papers: "Standards, Curriculum and Testing," "Student Discipline," "Teacher Preparation and Certification," "Elementary and Secondary Teacher Evaluation," "Teacher recruitment and Early career incentives"
- AFT Quest Conference, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Routine correspondence
- AFT Conference, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  January 1-18, 1987. Program for training conference, "School Reform: Realizing the Vision," 1987; Report of the AFT Task Force on the Future of Education, "The Revolution That is Overdue," 1986; AFT research report, "Collective Bargaining and Education Reform, January 16, 1987; correspondence; handwritten notes
- AFT Quest Conference, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  July 30 - August 2, 1987. Tentative program brochure; paper presented by Bob Pearlman, Boston Teachers Union, "National Situation Report: Summary of United States/AFT Report on Utilization of New Information Technologies in U.S. Schools"; "The Dutch NIVO Project: the New Computer Approach in Secondary Education"; "Computers in the French School System"; "Report of the Trade Unions for Education and Science in the Federal Republic of Germany to the Conference of IFFTU Industrialised Nation Affiliates on 'New Technologies in Education'"; related materials
- AFT Quest Consortium (folder 1), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  April 23-26, 1973. AFT QuEST (Quality Educational Standards in Teaching) Consortium Yearbook April 23-26, 1973. 1972; AFT QuEST Resource Notebook April 23-26, 1973
- AFT Quest Consortium (folder 2), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Publication for AFT QuEST Consortium on Educational Policy, April 3-5, 1972; occasional papers
- AFT Task Force on Future of Education, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Special order of business submitted by the Executive Council, "The Revolution That Is Overdue: Looking Toward the Future of Teaching and Learning," a report of the AFT Task Force on the Future of Education; memos
- Academic Freedom, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  NYSUT memo reporting on actions of Task Force on Academic Freedom, September 28, 1989; minutes of December 9-10, 1988, meeting; task force Statement of Principles; correspondence
- Academic Standards See: Curriculum Mandates, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Newspaper clippings from New York Times and Wall Street Journal
- Accountability (folder 1) See also: Evaluation See also: Assessment See also: Performance Assessment, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  "Problems in Using Pupil Outcomes for Teacher Evaluation," National Education Association, April 1975; address by Samuel P. Martin, M.D., at the October 1975 meeting of the Advisory Committee on Accreditation and Institutional Eligibility, "A Conceptual Look at the Role of the U.S. Commissioner of Education's Advisory Committee on Accreditation and Institutional Eligibility"; American Optometric Association Report to the House of Delegates, Council on Optometric Education, June 1, 1976; materials by Cooperative Accountability Project, including Survey on Educational Accountability for the Michigan State Department of Education, May 1974.
- Accountability (folder 2), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Brochure, "What Parents Should Know about Accountability!" by National Education Association (NEA); NEA memos; NEA paper, Criteria for Evaluating State Education Accountability Systems; paper, "An Assessment of the Michigan Accountability System," prepared for NEA and Michigan Education Association; paper, "A Response to the Michigan Education Department's Defense of Their Accountability System," August 27, 1974; presentation to the 1974 New Jersey Education Association Convention on Accountability and Teacher Evaluation; paper, "Accountability in Education," by James G. Ward, for Dr. David Axelrod
- Accountability (folder 3), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Materials for Denver Accountability Conference, 1973; internal draft by Educational Testing Service, "An Accountability Design for School Systems," June 1973; State of Florida, Articles on Educational Accountability in Universal English, revised February 1973
- Accountability – Educational Accountability, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Printed publications: Striving Toward Dialogue: A National Forum on Educational Accountability (produced by Cooperative Accountability Project in cooperation with NEA and AFT), Colorado Department of Education; Accounting for Accountability, Cooperative Accountability Project, Denver CO; Who's Afraid of Educational Accountability? Cooperative Accountability Project, Denver CO; Condition Variables in Relation to Measured Student Performance: The Use of Indicators in Pennsylvania, Cooperative Accountability Project, Denver CO; State Educational Accountability Repository (SEAR): A Program of the Cooperative Accountability Project, newsletter of the Cooperative Accountability Project, CAP Commentary, vol. 1, nos. 1, 3, 5, March, November 1974, September 1975; 1974 AFT convention resolution re accountability; remarks of Hon. Albert H. Quie, M.C., "Accountability and the Federal Interest in Education," before a conference of the Cooperative Accountability Project, January 31, 1975; agenda for a national forum on educational accountability, sponsored by the U.S. Office of Education and administered by the Cooperative Accountability Project, May 8-9, 1975
- Accountability – National Forum on Educational Accounting, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  May 18-19, 1975. Correspondence; printed publications: Keeping the Public Informed: Accent on Accountability; Cooperative Public Accountability Project: Roles of Participants in Educational Accountability; Cooperative Public Accountability Project: Legislation by the States: Accountability and Assessment in Education; Report and Recommendations of the MEA Task Force on Assessment and Accountability, March 1974; A Staff Response to the Report: An Assessment of the Michigan Accountability System, Michigan Department of Education, May 1974
- Accountability – Toni Cortese Cooperative Accountability Project, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Program agenda for National Forum on Educational Accountability; description of sponsors; Market Opinion Research report, "Survey on Educational Accountability for the Michigan State Department of Education" (stamped "Cooperative Accountability Project, Colorado Department of Education"), May 1974; topic papers for National Forum on Educational Accountability: "Goals and Objectives," "Assessment and Evaluation," and "Who Should Be Accountable to Whom and for What?"; speech delivered at National Forum by L. Wendell Rivers, Ph.D., "Psychoeducational Testing: The End of a Controversy?"; article reprints; list of participants
- Accountability – Regents School Improvement and Accountability Program, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Draft of legislation, Education Accountability Act; letters from Commissioner Sobol to the Board of Regents, outlining details of accountability program, requiring schools to develop five-year plans, annual reports on student achievement by race, independent reviews, and state intervention in underperforming schools
- Accountability – Excellence and Accountability Program – Albany SD See also: Excellence in Teaching, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  June 12, 1990. Descriptions of program; correspondence; status report, May 1990.
- Adult Education Advisory Council (folder 1), 1981-1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Correspondence as above
- Adult Education Advisory Council (folder 2), 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Report, "Community Education in the 1980's: The New York Agenda," Division of Continuing Education, May 13, 1981; related correspondence
- Adult Education Network, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  List of locals to receive mailing; reply card from network contact person; cover letter from vp Antonia Cortese
- Adult Learning Services Goals, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  June 2, 1981. Report by the State Education Commissioner's Advisory Council on Adult Learning Services, "Setting the Goals for the Future of Adult Learning in New York State: Background Paper for Regional Forums on Lifelong Learning," September 1980; summary of legislative bills; Testimony for New York State Assembly Committee on Higher education, "TAP for the Part-Time Student," by Dr. Robert E. Pennock, chairman, Association for Continuing Higher Education, Region II, November 21, 1978; Statement by Dr. Irwin H. Polishook, president, Professional Staff Congress/CUNY, Adult Learning Bills before the Board of Regents, January 29, 1981
- Adult Learning Legislation Meeting, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  January 29, 1981. Text of Memorandum in Support of "An Act to Amend the Education Law in Relation to Removing the Age 21 Limit to High School Attendance and Authorizing a Separate State Aid Formula for Adult Learning Programs Leading to a High School Diploma or the Equivalent"; memo from State Education Department to NYSUT president Tom Hobart asking for comments on proposed legislation
- Adult Learning Services Legislative Package, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)